A Guide to the Hugh N. McClure Circus Collection 1901-1986
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Hugh N. McClure Circus Collection 1901-1986
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13165
The Hugh N. McClure circus collection consists of ca. 606 items (2 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot) of memorabilia and ephemera related to circuses in America.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Crown Collectibles, Richmond, Virginia, November 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hugh N. McClure grew up in Staunton, Virginia, and worked as a businessman in Charlottesville. He once served as a director on the Circus Fans Association of America Board and because of his connection with the circus business, there were many circus stops in Virginia with some obvious partiality paid to performances in Charlottesville and Staunton.
Scope and Content
The Hugh N. McClure circus collection consists of ca. 606 items (2 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot) of memorabilia and ephemera related to circuses in America. McClure began a life-long love affair with the circus as a young boy growing up in Staunton, Virginia, in the 1930s and, as a young businessman living in Charlottesville, Virginia, he promoted circus performances in his state with great passion. He established friendships with many performers, owners, and others associated with the circus, including members of the Circus Fans Association. Materials in the collection include correspondence written to McClure, as well as a number of magazine and newspaper articles. There are also membership cards, posters, tickets, programs, route statements (travel and performance itineraries), and photographs of circus performers, employees, and animals. Some material comes from the collection of fellow fan Wallace A. ("Wally") Ahlberg.
The demise of the great American circus started in the early 1950s, the decade from which much of the collection dates. Correspondence from Virginia circus fans Ethel G. Cline, C.W. Glotzbach, William W. Old, and W. Wilson Poarch, touches on the changes in circuses brought on by the advent of television, labor costs and unionization, and other developments in American society. The periodical articles in the collection offer further insight into the changes in circuses (such as the discontinuation of using the large and expensive canvas "big top" tent) while at the same time often enthusiastically praising and describing the continued spectacle of circus pageantry even during the institution's decline.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following series: I. Hugh McClure Vintage Collection. II. Miscellaneous Circus Materials. Within Series I materials are generally arranged chronologically. Within Series II materials are arranged alphabetically and chronologically for correspondence.
Series I, Hugh McClure Vintage Collection, consists of circus memorabilia from the first half of the Twentieth Century accumulated by Hugh McClure
Series II, Miscellaneous Circus Materials, contains a large amount of correspondence between Hugh McClure and other circus fans as well as a large collection of newspaper and magazine article clippings on circus matters. There is also a large number of black and white photographs of circus performers, employees, and animals.
Contents List
- Series I: Hugh McClure Vintage Collection
  - Vintage Sign: Photographs Courtesy Bill Posting Dept. Ringling Bros. n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - The Great Adam Forepaugh Parade in 1888 n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Vintage Tickets and Passes 1954-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Official Program Gollmar Brothers Circus 1922 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Contracts and Other Circus Miscellanea 1911-1938 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Ringling Bros. Envelope and Tickets 1933 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Ringling Bros. Letter Opener 1933 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Circus Materials
  - Book Excerpts 1901, 1921 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Circus Fan Association Convention Program, Membership Cards, and Roster 1957-1961 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Circus Programs 1954-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, Wallace ("Wally") A. Ahlberg 1955-1962 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence, B-G 1955-1963 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence, M-Y 1954-1964 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles 1949-1959 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles 1953-1962, n.d.
  - Newspaper Articles 1960, 1985-1986
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles 1960-1965, 1985 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Manuscripts: Personal Reminiscences and Circus History (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Miscellaneous Items (Sales Lists, Circus Acts Promotional Brochures, Advertising Contracts, Postcards, Calendar) 1955-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Photographs (8x10, black and white, Animals, Clowns, Jugglers, Trapeze Artists) n.d. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Photographs (black and white, many credited to Charles F. Miles) 1937, 1954-1956 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Route Statements and Route Cards of Various Circuses 1954-1957 (Box-folder 2:3)